Finding Aid for Chrystal G. Tibbs papers, 1913-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chrystal G. Tibbs papers 1913-2013 1990-2013
Tibbs, Chrystal G.
2013119 Aa 2 UAl
The Chrystal G. Tibbs Papers comprise over a half-century of documents pertaining to Tibbs's membership in various chapters of the Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority and to the history of the sorority at large. Founded at Howard University in 1908, A.K.A. was the first sorority established by African-American women and currently has approximately 250,000 members. The collection's six series contain papers pertaining to Tibbs's personal participation in sorority activities (including those related to her tenure in various administrative posts), materials from several Michigan chapters, sorority publications, and audiovisual materials.
4 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated to the library by Dr. Chrystal G. Tibbs (Donor No. 10957 ) in 2013.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Chrystal Tibbs is a retired elementary school administrator and lifetime member of the Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority. A longtime Michigan resident, Tibbs spent her career in the Detroit Public School system and has been active in numerous Michigan chapters of A.K.A. for five decades. Chrystal Garrell Powell Tibbs was born on May 17th, 1932, in Williamsport, Pennsylvania to Robert Bernard Powell and Maggie Winchester Winstead Powell. Tibbs graduated valedictorian of her class at the Charles Sumner School in Parkersburg, West Virginia in 1949. She subsequently attended Bluefield State College (1949-51) and Oberlin College (1951-52) before obtaining her B.S. in Elementary Education in 1955 from Wayne State University. She earned a Master's of Education in 1962, also from Wayne State, followed by a Master of Arts in Library Science from the University of Michigan in 1968 and a PhD in Education from Michigan State University in 1974. Tibbs served in administrative capacities at various Detroit elementary schools and as Principal of Hampton Elementary School.
Membership in the Alpha Kappa Alpha sorority spans multiple generations of Tibbs's family; her mother, three maternal aunts, three sisters, and two daughters have all been members. Tibbs first became a member of A.K.A. in 1950 while at Bluefield State College, where she was inducted into the Beta Omicron chapter. Upon her marriage and subsequent move to Detroit, Tibbs became a member of the Alpha Rho Omega chapter, for which she was later elected to the offices of Anti-Basileus (Vice President), Epistoleus (Corresponding Secretary), and Member at Large. In 1991 Tibbs became a charter member of the Tau Alpha Omega chapter of Redford, Michigan, where she has served as Basileus (President), Anti-Basileus, and Philacter (Sergeant at Arms). In 2008 Tibbs served as President of the Vision Fair Foundation, a charitable organization under the auspices of the Tau Alpha Omega chapter.
Tibbs became a Golden Soror (50 year member of A.K.A.) in 2000 and was awarded the Golden Soror of the Year award in 2009. She has been a delegate to dozens of regional and national conferences and events over a fifty-year span. Tibbs was appointed Great Lakes Regional Representative to the International Archives Committee of A.K.A. in 2009, a post to which she has been reappointed twice and which she will hold until 2014. In this capacity Tibbs has worked to educate A.K.A. members with regard to archival practice and preservation of the history of the sorority, its chapters, and its membership.
The Chrystal G. Tibbs Papers comprise materials accumulated through Tibbs's participation in Alpha Kappa Alpha conferences, chapter meetings, and special interest groups at the local, state, regional, and national level over a span of fifty years. The activities of Michigan-based chapters are particularly well represented. The collection is divided into five series: Personal Papers and Artifacts, A.K.A. National and Regional Activities, Michigan Chapter Activities, Publications, and Audiovisual Materials.
Subjects:
Tibbs, Chrystal G.; African American women--College students.; African American women--Educators--Michigan.; African American women--School principals--Michigan--Hampton (Township); African American women--Societies and clubs.; Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority.; Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority. Alpha Rho Omega Chapter (Detroit, Mich.); Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority. International Archives Committee.; Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority. Tau Alpha Omega Chapter (Redford, Mich.); Grace Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Greek letter societies--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Tibbs, Chrystal G.; African American women.; African American women--Societies and clubs.; African Americans--Women.; Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority--History.; Fraternities and sororities.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
African American women--Societies and clubs.; Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority.; Fraternities and sororities.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; DVDs.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Personal Papers and Artifacts
  The Personal Papers and Artifacts series (0.9 linear feet) is divided into four subseries: A.K.A. Membership Papers, Awards, and the Maggie Powell Papers. The first subseries is composed of certificates of membership and merit, notes and photographs from conferences and events Tibbs attended, and a scrapbook celebrating Tibbs's educational, professional, and A.K.A.-related achievements. The second subseries contains placards and trophies Tibbs was awarded in recognition of her long-term service to the sorority. The last subseries contains the papers of Tibbs's mother, Maggie Powell, who became a member of A.K.A. in 1925. These include certificates, speeches, press clippings, and photographs. The last subseries is unrelated to Alpha Kappa Alpha and predominantly consists of ephemera and mid-20th century photographs from a Detroit church which Tibbs attended.
  - A.K.A. Membership Papers
    - Membership certificates and cards 1950s, 1988, 1991, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Certificates of merit, attendance, completion 1997-2013, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Speeches 1987, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Notes from conferences and events 2002, 2003, 2011 (Box 1)
    - Event invitations 1991, 1999, 2006-2013 (Box 1)
    - Personal correspondence 2011 undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs 1980s-2012, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Golden Soror scrapbook album 2009 (oversize) (Box 5)
  - Awards
    - Tile in recognition of service, Great Lakes Regional Conference 1987 (Box 4)
    - Soror with the longest membership, legacy award placard from the Eta Iota Omega Chapter 1999 (Box 4)
    - Golden Soror placard commemorating 56 years of service 2006 (Box 4)
    - Golden Soror of the Year trophy 2009 (Box 4)
    - Appreciation award from the Tau Alpha Omega Chapter 2013 (Box 4)
  - Maggie Powell Papers
    - Biographical sketches 2000 (Box 1)
    - Membership certificates (facsimiles) 1925, 1943, 1966, 1976, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Speeches 2002, 2008 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1952, 1998, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Press clippings 1949, 1952, 1976, 2000s (Box 1)
    - Photographs 1986, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Grace Episcopal Church Records
    - Directories 1964, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter 1982 (Box 3)
    - Reverend H.A. Stines, program and clippings 1964 (Box 3)
    - Memorial service programs 1977, 2004, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Photographs of church events 1940s-1960s, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Ephemera 1955, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Guild of the Christ Child, invitation to Tibbs's daughter Nadine 1954 (Box 3)
- A.K.A. National and Regional Activities
  The A.K.A. National and Regional Activities series (0.8 linear feet) is divided into three subseries: National Level Activities and Documents, A.K.A. International Archives Committee (I.A.C.), and the Great Lakes Region. The first subseries includes policy documents, programs and ephemera from national events (particularly Boules), photographs, and newspaper clippings. The second subseries contains papers pertaining to the sorority's national and regional efforts to preserve its history, as well as documents from Tibbs's tenure as Great Lakes Regional Representative to the I.A.C. Such documents include histories, conference presentations, and committee meeting proceedings. The third subseries is composed of materials related to activities of A.K.A.'s Great Lakes Region, including Great Lakes Regional Conferences and regional histories.
  - National Level Activities and Documents
    - Articles of Incorporation (copy) 1913 (Box 1)
    - Directorate and membership information 2013 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 2010 (Box 1)
    - Manuals of standard procedure 1992, 2010 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1980s-2013, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Seven panoramic photographs 1947, 1948, 1950, 1955, 1961 undated (located in oversize folder, UAl) (Box 1)
    - National events
      - Boule programs (national conference convening biannually, previously annually)
        - 1948 (Box 1)
        - 1958 (Box 1)
        - 1962 (Box 1)
        - 2006 (Box 1)
        - Assorted Boule events programs 1994, 1996, 2000, 2008 (Box 1)
        - Boule workshop report 1964 (Box 1)
      - Founder's Day programs 1978, 2000s (Box 1)
      - Leadership seminars 1991, 2007, 2009, 2010 (Box 1)
  - A.K.A. International Archives Committee (I.A.C.)
    - A.K.A. National Archives, Moorland-Spingarn Research Center at Howard University 1978, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Moorland-Spingarn Research Center, articles and correspondence 2009 (Box 1)
    - Record book of sorority events dating from 1918-2011 (Box 1)
    - A.K.A. sorority histories (written by Tibbs) 2003 (Box 1)
    - "A.K.A.'s Unforgettable Unsung Sorors of the Civil Rights Movement" (exhibit pamphlets, photographs) 2012 (Box 1)
    - Histories and biographies pertaining to A.K.A.'s involvement in the Civil Rights Movement 2013 (Box 1)
    - I.A.C. Great Lakes Regional Conference workshop (presented by Tibbs) 2010 (Box 1)
    - I.A.C. leadership conference presentations 2011 (including "Archiving Timeless Treasures" workshop led by Tibbs) (Box 1)
    - I.A.C. leadership conference presentations 2013 (including one led by Tibbs) (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Regional Archives committee meeting (including disaster preparation workshop led by Tibbs) 2012 (Box 1)
    - I.A.C. committee meeting agendas, reports, correspondence 2003-2013 (Box 1)
    - Excellence in Strategic Preservation Competition 2010 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of I.A.C. events 2013 (Box 1)
  - A.K.A. Great Lakes Region
    - Great Lakes Regional Conferences
      - 1991 program (Box 1)
      - 1992 program (Box 1)
      - 1998 program (Box 1)
      - 1999 program (Box 1)
      - 2003 workshop (Box 1)
      - Planning documents 1980-2009, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Assorted documents pertaining to Great Lakes regional activities 2001, 2012 (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Heritage Training document 2009 (Box 1)
    - Every Chapter's History is Precious: A History of the "Great" Great Lakes Region, 1924-2010, edited by Octavia Walters Cabey, 2010 (Box 1)
    - A.K.A. Sorority Great Lakes Region: Through the Years, by Bella G. Clinkscale, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Pearl Times (Great Lakes Region periodical) 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Regional Directors
      - Eva L. Evans 1994 undated (Box 1)
      - Schylbea Jean Hopkins 2005 (Box 1)
- A.K.A. Michigan Chapter Activities
  The Michigan Chapter Activities series (1.3 linear feet) is divided into four subseries: Statewide Activities, the Tau Alpha Omega Chapter, the Alpha Rho Omega Chapter, and Other Michigan Chapters. The first subseries contains programs of events, such as the Michigan Cluster Conference, and obituaries of Michigan members. The second subseries is comprised of events programs, membership rosters, and documents from Tibbs's tenure as Basileus of the Tau Alpha Omega Chapter of Redford, Michigan. The latter documents include meeting minutes, annual reports, and records regarding charitable initiatives. The third subseries is predominantly comprised of events programs and ephemera from the Alpha Rho Omega Chapter of Detroit. The fourth subseries contains documents, events programs, and ephemera from thirteen other Michigan chapters, which are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Statewide Activities
    - Michigan Cluster Conferences
      - 2006-2010 (Box 2)
      - 2011 (Box 2)
      - 2012 (Box 2)
      - 25th and 26th Michigan cluster and undergraduate roundup 2000, 2001 (Box 2)
      - Report of the cluster coordinator 2000 (Box 2)
    - Day at the Capitol, 4 folders
      - 2004 (Box 2)
      - 2008 (Box 2)
      - 2010, 2011 (Box 2)
      - 2012, 2013 (Box 2)
    - Michigan-based A.K.A. members
      - Assorted members 2006, 2013 (Box 2)
      - Obituaries 2005-2013, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Memorial service programs 1979-2013, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Tau Alpha Omega Chapter (Redford, MI)
    - Bylaws 1997, 2004, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Summary of chapter history and leaders 2009 (Box 2)
    - Tau Alpha Omega Charitable Fund, legal documents 1995 (Box 2)
    - Events 2001-2009 (Box 2)
    - Ivy Inquirer (periodical) 2008-2009, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Membership rosters, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Chapter documents (agendas, minutes, reports)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 2)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 2)
      - 2007 (Box 2)
      - 2008, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Annual report 2008 (Box 2)
      - Chapter report 2008 (Box 2)
      - 2009, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Chapter report 2009 (Box 2)
    - Vision Fair Foundation
      - Bylaws 2009 (Box 2)
      - Event programs 2003, 2009, 2010, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Documents (agendas, minutes, correspondence)
        - 2006-2007 (Box 2)
        - 2008, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - 2009 (Box 2)
        - 2010 (Box 2)
  - Alpha Rho Omega Chapter (Detroit, MI)
    - Bylaws 1981 (Box 2)
    - Press clippings 1986, 1990 undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs 1940s-1970s (Box 2)
    - Events
      - Programs 1954, 1980s, 1994, 1997, 2006-2012 (Box 2)
      - 75th anniversary celebration 1997 (Box 2)
      - 90th anniversary celebration 2012 (Box 2)
      - June Breakfasts 1951, 1998, 2002-2012, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hertha Priest Jenkins, resume and press clippings 1938, 1941, 1949, 1985, 2006 (Box 2)
    - Local interest groups
      - A.K.A. Foundation of Detroit, bylaws and events 1999 (Box 2)
      - R.E.N.E.W. of A.K.A. (Responsible Experienced Naturally Elegant Women) 1991 (Box 2)
  - Other Michigan Chapters
    - Beta Mu (Detroit, MI) 1955, 1996, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Delta Psi Omega (Ann Arbor, MI) 1949, 1950, 1964, 1976, 2008, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Delta Tau Omega (Lansing, MI) 1950s, 1962, 1977, 1998, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Eta Iota Omega (Inkster, MI) and Xi (Detroit, MI) 1978, 1986, 2000s
      - Tanner Johnson Livisay (1906-2004), biographical sketches and documents 1920s (facsimiles), 2004 (Box 3)
    - Eta Upsilon Omega (Saginaw, MI) 2010 (Box 3)
    - Iota Sigma Omega (Kalamazoo, MI) 1984, 2010, 2011 (Box 3)
    - Lambda Pi Omega (Detroit, MI)
      - Documents 2008, 2010, 2013 (Box 3)
      - Basilei and chapter history 2009 (Box 3)
      - Excellence in Strategic Preservation, chapter outline 2009 (Box 3)
    - Mu Alpha Omega (Midland, MI) 2010 (Box 3)
    - Nu Phi Omega (Muskegon, MI) 2001 (Box 3)
    - Pi Tau Omega (Southfield, MI) and Pi Delta (Franklin Village, MI) 1998, 2009, 2011 (Box 3)
    - Psi Kappa Omega (Battle Creek, MI) 2010 (Box 3)
    - Theta Lambda Omega (Pontiac, MI)
      - Events 2010 (Box 3)
      - 38th annual debutante scholarship cotillion 2010 (Box 3)
      - 39th annual debutante scholarship cotillion 2011 (Box 3)
    - Zeta Beta Omega (Flint, MI) and Xi Phi (Dearborn, MI) 1945-1962, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Assorted Detroit and Ann Arbor chapters 1938, 1945, 1957, 2008 (Box 3)
    - Ivy Leaf Magazine clippings pertaining to assorted Michigan chapters 1944-1968, 1978 (Box 3)
- Publications
  The Publications series (0.7 linear feet) is comprised of two subseries: Ivy Leaf Magazine and Books. The former subseries contains issues of A.K.A.'s national publication entitled the Ivy Leaf. The latter subseries contains books published by A.K.A. and devoted to the topics of the sorority's early history, its notable members, and the professional and political accomplishments of African-American women.
  - Ivy Leaf Magazine
    - 1942 (Box 3)
    - 1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944 (Box 3)
    - 1945 (Box 3)
    - 1946 (Box 3)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996 (Box 3)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - In 4 folders: (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority: 1908-1958, by Marjorie H. Parker, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha Through the Years: 1908-1988, by Marjorie H. Parker, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha: In the Eye of the Beholder, by Marjorie H. Parker, 1979 (accompanied by reading and study guide, 1981) (Box 3)
    - A Love that Equals my Labors: the Life Story of Norma E. Boyd, by Norma E. Boyd, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Heritage series 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5: Women in the judiciary, politics, business, medicine, dentistry, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Heritage series no. 6: founders, incorporators, and past supreme basilei, 1976 (Box 3)
    - African American women heritage series numbers 1 and 2: physicians and judges, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Inspired to Victory's Heights: A.K.A. Sorority's Honorary Members 1913 Through 1990, 1991 (Box 3)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Materials series (0.3 linear feet) contains media in a variety of formats, including VHS, DVD, and CD-ROM. The VHS tapes and DVD consist of short films commemorating A.K.A.'s history, while the more numerous CD-ROMs contain information about Boules, campaign presentations of prospective Basilei, and information about archival practices undertaken to document the sorority's history. The series also contains one record of A.K.A. sorority songs.
  - A.K.A. Sorority Songs (45 RPM record), 1 phonograph records 45 rpm (Box 4)
  - A.K.A., Sisterhood and Service: the First Century 2008, 1 optical disks DVDs (Box 4)
  - VHS Tapes
    - The First Member: Ethel Hedgeman Lyle-the story of her life and the vision that led to the founding of A.K.A. sorority undated, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - The Legacy Revisited: We Pledge Ourselves to Remember (slide presentation) 1994, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
    - Tau Alpha Omega, A.K.A. Sorority Founder's Day 10th anniversary celebration 2001, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)
  - CD-ROMs
    - 62nd Boule, minutes 2006, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - 63rd Boule 2008, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - 64th Boule 2010, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - 65th Boule 2012, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - 77th Great Lakes Regional Conference 2008, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Great Lakes undergraduate roundup signage committee 2009, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Barbara Anne McKinzie, Supreme Basileus: the journey to supreme leadership, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Altha Steen, candidate for Basileus, presentation 2001, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Integrating the archives into chapter operations 2008, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - "Simply...the best" archives regional promotion 2010, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Ivy Leaf, digital edition sample 2007, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Tau Alpha Omega, unspecified event 2006, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)
    - Tau Alpha Omega, unspecified event 2006, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 4)